Guide to the Parliamentary Speeches, Debates, Etc.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Parliamentary speeches, debates, etc., and other miscellaneous manuscripts]
1640-1645
OSBORN FB156
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.19
(1 volume)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb156. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
- Osborn fb156
  - HALSALL, JAMES
    - [Statement to House of Lords], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      [1642 Jun 10]
      1 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS, signed Ja: Halsall.
      Concerning a Proclamation against
      the Militia.
      LJ, V, 124.
      f.1-2
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Order to a committee], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642/3 Mar 15]
      Contemporary MS, signed H. Elsyng,
      Clerk of Parliament. Ordered to
      reconcile the Lords' and Commons'
      versions of an article in the
      cessation treaty.
      LJ, III, 2.
      f.3-4.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - [Answer to the Yorkshire Petition], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 Apr 12]
      2 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy.
      On measures taken by Parliament to
      restore unity and peace.
      LJ, IV, 713.
      f.5-6.
  - YORKSHIRE, ENGLAND, CITIZENS.
    - [Petition to Parliament], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 Apr]
      1 p.; 40 x 30 cm.
      Contemporary MS.
      Declaration of their support of
      Parliament and their desire that
      King and Parliament come to an
      understanding.
      LJ, IV, 711.
      f. 7-8.
  - YORKSHIRE, ENGLAND, CITIZENS.
    - [Petition to, and answer from, Charles I, King of Great Britain (1600-1649)] (Box 1)
      [1642 Apr 7]
      Petition to the King for Peace, and
      the King's response.
      Signed by Sir Edward Nicholas
      (1593-1669).
      LJ, IV, 710.
      f.9-10.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Letter to Mr William Booth of Lines], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 May 24]
      Orders Booth to remain in
      Lincolnshire until called upon to
      attend the King.
      LJ, V, 128.
      f.11-12.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - [Order to stay arms going to York], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 May 28]
      1 p.; 30 x 18 cm.
      Contemporary MS signed by John
      Browne, clerk of Parliament.
      LJ, V, 89.
      f. 13-14.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - [Order to prevent the levying of troops by the King], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy, signed by John
      LJ, V, 90.
      f. 15-16.
  - PELHAM, SIR WILLIAM
    - [Letter to Lord Willoughbie], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 Jun 4]
      Contemporary MS copy, in part in the
      hand of John Browne. To Francis
      Willoughby, 5th baron Willoughby of
      Parham (1613?-1666). Refuses to
      give up his magazine to Parliament.
      f.17-18.
  - LITTLETON, EDWARD, 1ST BARON LITTLETON, 1589-1645
    - [Letter to Lord Willoughby], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 Jun 7]
      Contemporary MS copy. To Francis
      Parham (1613?-1666). Denies voting
      for the Militia Ordinance.
      f.19-20.
  - TURWHITT, SIR PHILLIPP
    - [Letter to Lord Willoughby], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 Jun 8]
      surrender magazine to Parliament.
      f.21-22.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - [Letter from Amsterdam reported to Parliament], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1642 Jun 12]
      3 p.; 30 x 19 cm. and 19 x 15 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Anonymous
      letter reporting on the pawning of
      jewels to buy munitions. Includes
      list of weapons and supplies.
      LJ, X, 126.
      f. 23-24.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - [Letter from Amsterdam to John Beauchamp, Merchant of London] (Box 1)
      [1642 Jun 13]
      Contemporary MS copy. Written to
      Parliament concerning cloth trade
      and munitions being conveyed to the
      north.
      LJ, V, 126.
      f.25-26.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Commission of Array for Leicestershire], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. In Latin.
      LJ, V, 147.
      f.27-28.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Letter sent with the Commission of Array to Leicestershire], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      3 p.; 31 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Forbids
      subjects to put the militia ordinance
      of Parliament into effect; gives
      authority to three people to muster
      the trained bands (Henry Hastings,
      earl of Huntingdon [1586-1643]; Henry
      Hastings; William Courtenay, earl of
      Devon [1628-1702]).
      f.29-30.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1640. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Report by the Committee on Irish Affairs], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1640 Jul 16]
      2 p.; 30 x 18 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Propositions
      for regaining Limerick.
      CJ, III, 677.
      f.31-32.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Debate with Thomas Wriothesley, 4th earl of Southampton (1607-1667) concerning a message from the King, 1642 Aug 27], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      f.33-36.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - "The declaration sent to the States of Holland, 1642 Sept 25." (Box 1)
      Concerning Holland's stance in the
      conflict between King and Parliament.
      LJ, V, 372.
      f.37-38.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1642.
    - "Declaration of both Houses of Parliament concerning the Commission of Array, 1642 July 1.", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      26 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Arguments against the King's
      Commission of Array for
      Leicestershire.
      Rushworth, iv, 661.
      f.39-53.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-1674
    - [Speech at a Conference of both Houses of Parliament against the Council in the North, 1641 April 22], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      17 p.; 30 x 18 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Rushworth,
      v.4, 230.
      f.54-62.
  - FINCH, JOHN FINCH, 1ST BARON, 1584-1660
    - [The speech of the Lord Keeper at the opening of Parliament, 1640 Nov 3], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      9 p.; 30 x 18 cm.
      v.4, 12.
      f.63-70.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1644.
    - [Answer to the Paper of the Scottish Commissioners, 1643/4 Mar 9], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      4 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Agreement on
      the covenant, the Assembly of
      Divines, and on payments to the
      Scottish army.
      LJ, VI, 461.
      f.71-72.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - [Declaration to the Scots, 1643 June 27], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      3 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      On sending commissioners in Scotland
      to negotiate.
      LJ, VI, 112.
      f.73-74.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1644.
    - [Additional instructions for the Parliamentary Commissioners in Scotland, 1643/4 Mar 9] (Box 1)
      11 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Instructions on negotiations, and
      grants of powers of taxation and
      investigation to the commissioners.
      f.75-82.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - [Instructions for Parliament's Commissioners at Oxford concerning the Scots' Commissioners, 1643 April 11], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      LJ, V, 713.
      f.83-84.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - "Instructions agreed on by the Lords and Commons in Parliament for John Corbett, esq. sent into the Kingdom of Scotland by them" (Box 1)
      [1643 Jun 27]
      Contemporary MS copy. On preserving
      good relations between the two
      Kingdoms.
      LJ, VI, 113.
      f.85-86.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - [Letter of credence for John Corbett to the Lords of the Secret council of Scotland, 1643 June 27] (Box 1)
      f.87-88.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - [Letter to the Scottish Privy Council concerning the Earl of Antrim, 1643 June 27], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. Request
      Randall MacDonnell, 2nd earl and 1st
      marquis of Antrim (1609-1683) be
      returned to England to stand trial.
      f.89-90.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Declaration against six Scottish Lords, 1643 July 19], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS (draft copy).
      Declaration against six Lords as
      incendiaries for treating with the
      Queen.
      CJ, III, 79 and LJ, VI, 137.
      f.91
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - [Letter of Credence to the Lords of the Scottish Council for the Commissioners of Parliament, 1643 July 19], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Scotland Privy Council.
      LJ, VI, 139.
      f.92-93.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1643.
    - [Letter to the Earl of Leven, 1643 July 19], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 30 x 20 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Request that
      Alexander Leslie, 1st earl of Leven
      (1580?-1661) take command of the
      Scottish army if it is sent to assist
      Parliament.
      f.94-95.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1645.
    - [Address to Charles I, King of Great Britain (1600-1649) from both Houses of Parliament and the Scots Commissioners] (Box 1)
      [1644/5 Jan 17]
      Concerning the negotiations for
      peace to be held at Uxbridge.
      LJ, VII, 143.
      f.96-97.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1645.
    - [Appointment of additional commissioners to treat with the King], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1644/5 Jan 28]
      1 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Commissioners
      to treat with Charles I upon the
      propositions concerning religion
      only.
      LJ, VII, 159.
      f.98-99.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1645.
    - [Three papers addressed to the English Parliament concerning the Scottish army], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1644/5 Mar 19]
      5 p.; 29 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copies. Concerning
      the Scottish army in Ireland, arrears
      due to the army, and its maintenance.
      Signed "Jo.Cheislie" and "Jo.Cheisly."
      LJ, VII, 282.
      f.100-105.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1644.
    - [Letter to the Parliament of Scotland] (Box 1)
      [1644 May 25]
      Address of thanks to Scots for their
      assistance and on the settlement of
      the treaties between the two nations.
      LJ, VI. 568.
      f.106-109.
  - SCOTLAND. PARLIAMENT, 1644.
    - "Copy of the commission granted by the Parliament of Scotland to their commissioners at London," (Box 1)
      [1644 Jul 16]
      1 p.; 37 x 29 cm.
      LJ, VI, 681.
      f.110-111.
  - FAIRFAX, FERDINANDO FAIRFAX, 2ND BARON OF, 1584-1648
    - [Letter to Lord Leven concerning the surrender of Carlisle, and Leven's reply] (Box 1)
      [1645 Jun 21 & 23]
      Contemporary MS copies. To Alexander
      Leslie, 1st earl of Leven
      (1580?-1661) concerning Sir Thomas
      Glemham's query (d.1649?) about
      surrendering Carlisle, Eng. to
      Parliamentary forces.
      LJ, VII, 464.
      f.112-113.
  - ESSEX, ROBERT DEVEREUX, 3RD EARL OF, 1591-1646
    - [Letters to Prince Maurice and to Parliament on treating with the King, 1644 Aug 10] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 30 x 20 cm.
      MS copies in the hand of John Browne.
      LJ, VI, 671.
      f.114-115.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1645.
    - [Report from the committee for the Admiralty and Cinque Ports, 1645 Sept. 19] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 31 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy. Resolutions on
      restitution of a French ship and on
      the Ordinance for Martial Law by Sea.
      LJ, VII, 589.
      f.116-117.
  - ARMYNE, W.
    - [Letter to the Committee of Both Kingdoms], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 29 x 18 cm.
      Informing the members of the
      committee of a shipment of coal from
      Newcastle-upon-Tyne for the use of
      the London poor, 1644 Nov 22.
      LJ, VII, 88.
      f.118-119.
  - LEVEN, ALEXANDER LESLIE, 1ST EARL OF, 1580?-1661
    - [Letter to the Committee of Both Kingdoms on sending assistance to Sir W. Brereton at Chester, 1645 April 22] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 30 x 21 cm.
      LJ, VII, 343.
      f.122-123.
  - ESSEX, ROBERT DEVEREUX, 3RD EARL OF, 1591-1646
    - "The declaration of the Lord general at the surrendering of his commission, 1645 April 2." (Box 1)
      2 p.; 29 x 18 cm.
      LJ, VII, 300.
      f. 124-125.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1645. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Head for the Conference with the House of Commons about the Lord general, etc.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1645 Apr 2]
      Concerning the resignation of the
      Lord general.
      LJ, VII, 301.
      f.126-127.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1645. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Orders and resolutions concerning the Scottish army] (Box 1)
      [1645 May 10]
      Contemporary MS copy. Concerning
      southern advance of Scottish army
      and provisions for it.
      CJ, IV, 137 under 1643 May 9.
      f.128-129.
  - RUSSELL, ROBERT
    - [Letter to Robert Rich, 2nd earl of Warwick (1587-1658) concerning war news and a request for reinforcements for the defense of Guernsey, 1645 Sep 16] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 33 x 22 cm.
      LJ, VII, 594.
      f.130-131.
  - MANGLER, FRANCIS
    - [A report of Captain Francis Mangler's information about the King's Fleet destined against Guernsey, 1645 Sept. 23] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 31 x 22 cm.
      LJ, VII, 593.
      f.132.
  - GUERNSEY, ENGLAND. CITIZENS.
    - [Petition to the Committee of Both Kingdoms for assistance against the King's Fleet, 1645 Sept. 13], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      LJ, VII, 590.
      f.133-134.
  - GUERNSEY, ENGLAND. CITIZENS.
    - [Petition to the Committee of Both Kingdoms on the regulation of the wool industry, and their desire that the Earl of Warwick continue as their governor, 1645 Aug. 31] (Box 1)
      LJ, VII, 597.
      f.135-136.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1645.
    - [Paper presented to the Parliament of England, 1645 Oct 2] (Box 1)
      A promise to answer soon Parliament's
      request for military aid.
      LJ, VII, 630.
      f.137-138.
  - FLANDERS. GOVERNOR.
    - [A translation of a letter from the Governor of Flanders to Parliament, Brussels, 1645 Oct 28] (Box 1)
      On trade and restitution of ships.
      LJ, VII, 714.
      f.139-140.
  - GLAMORGAN, WALES. CITIZENS.
    - "A Declaration of the Knights, gentlemen, and freeholders of the county of Glamorgan the 25th of October 1645." (Box 1)
      Declaration of support for
      LJ, VII, 682.
      f.141-142.
  - RUSSIA COMPANY, LONDON.
    - [Petition to the Committee of Both Kingdoms, 1645 Nov 11], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 31 x 18 cm.
      From the governor and company of
      Russia merchants to the Committee
      asking that the Russian minister be
      given a proper reception.
      LJ, VII, 695.
      f.143-144.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Letter to Parliament desiring that his commissioners be given passes to come to London to treat for peace, 1645 Dec 15] (Box 1)
      LJ, VIII, 46.
      f.145-146.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1646.
    - [Negotiations between the Commissioners sent into Ireland by Parliament and the Duke of Ormonde, 1646 Nov 15-22] (Box 1)
      99 p.; 30 x 20 cm.
      Contemporary MS copies.
      36 documents, some pages blank,
      frayed edges, and some text lost. On
      the surrender of Dublin and other
      garrisons to Parliament. James
      Butler, 1st duke of Ormonde
      (1610-1685), Thomas Wharton, Richard
      Salwey (1615-1685), Sir John
      Clotworthy (d. 1665), Sir Robert King
      (1599?-1657), Robert Meredith.
      Rushworth, vi, 420-443.
      f.149-198.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647.
    - [Letter to the Parliament of Scotland desiring the delivery of Belfast to the English Forces, 1646/7 Feb 5] (Box 1)
      LJ, VIII, 708.
      f.199-200.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1645. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Information on the Speaker of the House of Commons on the Scots commissioners' refusal to receive Parliament's letter, 1646 Dec 2], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Document, signed "H.Elsynge".
      LJ, IV, 736.
      f.201-202.
  - LONDON. CORPORATION. COURT OF THE COMMON COUNCIL.
    - [Message to Parliament, 1647 June 15], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      A narrative of the Common Council's
      meeting with Thomas Fairfax, 3rd
      baron (1612-1671), and a demand that
      all levies of soldiers in London be
      stopped.
      LJ, IX, 274.
      f.203-204.
  - FAIRFAX, THOMAS FAIRFAX, 3RD BARON, 1612-1671
    - [Letter from Sir Thomas Fairfax and the Council of War to the City of London, 1647 June 14] (Box 1)
      Demand that the City prevent levies
      of men to oppose the Army.
      LJ, IX, 275.
      f.205-206.
  - LONDON. CORPORATION. COURT OF THE COMMON COUNCIL.
    - [Petition to Parliament, 1647 June 11], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Asking that the Army not be permitted
      to quarter in the City.
      LJ, IX, 256.
      f.207-208.
  - FAIRFAX, THOMAS FAIRFAX, 3RD BARON, 1612-1671
    - [Letter from Sir Thomas Fairfax and other officers of the Army to the Mayor, Aldermen, and Common Council of the City of London, 1647 June 10] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 20 x 19 cm.
      Assurances that although the Army is
      drawing towards London, it will not
      injure the City.
      LJ, IX, 257.
      f.209-210.
  - LONDON. CORPORATION. COURT OF THE COMMON COUNCIL.
    - [Letter to Thomas Fairfax, 3rd baron (1612-1671) and the Council of War, 1647 June 18] (Box 1)
      On preserving good relations
      between the Army and the City and
      LJ, IX, 281.
      f.211-212.
  - FAIRFAX, THOMAS FAIRFAX, 3RD BARON, 1612-1671
    - [Letter from Sir Thomas Fairfax and the Council of War to the Mayor, Aldermen, and Common Council of the City of London, 1647 June 15] (Box 1)
      Assurances that the Army will leave
      London as soon as it gains
      satisfaction from Parliament.
      f.213-214.
  - LONDON. CORPORATION. COURT OF THE COMMON COUNCIL.
    - [Order to acquaint Parliament with a letter that the Common Council intends to send to Thomas Fairfax, 3rd baron (1612-1671), 1647 June 18] (Box 1)
      Contemporary scribal MS. Signed
      "Michel".
      LJ, IX, 280.
      f.215-216.
  - WALLER, SIR HARDRESS, 1604?-1666?
    - [A Declaration presented by Sir Hardress Waller and other officers to the House of Lords, 1647/8 Jan 17] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 29 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copies (2) in the
      hand of John Browne. A declaration
      that the Army will uphold the rights
      and privileges of the peers of
      England, followed by a declaration
      of thanks from the Lords.
      LJ, IX, 664. (The Army's declaration
      is mentioned but not printed in the
      Journal.)
      f.217.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1648.
    - [Resolutions of Both Houses of Parliament not to alter the form of government and to maintain the covenant, 1648 May 6] (Box 1)
      MS copy in the hand of John Browne.
      LJ, X, 247.
      f.218.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647.
    - [Orders of Parliament and of the Committee of Both Kingdoms concerning the propositions to be sent to the King, 1647 Nov 20 & 22] (Box 1)
      Document signed by Walter? Frost.
      CJ, V, 366.
      f.220-221.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Resolutions and memorandum] (Box 1)
      Document, signed by Walter? Frost.
      Resolution of the Commons on the
      answer to be given to the Scots
      commissioners, 1647 Dec 15, followed
      by a memorandum by Frost noting that
      the answer was delivered to the
      Committee of Both Kingdoms, 1647 Dec
      16.
      CJ, V, 386.
      f.222-223.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647.
    - [Order by the Committee of Lords and Commons and the Committee for the Militia for the City of London to assemble forces in the city, 1647 June 12] (Box 1)
      f.224-225.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647.
    - [Narrative of the discourse between the Commissioners of Parliament and Charles I, King of Great Britain (1600-1649), when they presented the propositions for peace to him at Hampton Court, 1647 Sept 14] (Box 1)
      LJ, IX, 434.
      f.226-227.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647.
    - [Paper to be presented to the Scots commissioners, 1647 Oct 26], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Acquainting the Scots with the
      Peace propositions to be sent to
      Charles I, King of Great Britain,
      1600-1649.
      LJ, IX, 495.
      f.228-229.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1647.
    - [Order of Parliament to communicate the peace proposition to the Commissioners of Scotland, 1647 Nov 11] (Box 1)
      LJ, IX, 518.
      f.230-231.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1646.
    - "The Answers sent to the King", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1645/6 Jan 16]
      3 p.; 29 x 18 cm.
      Negotiations on the Parliament's
      peace propositions sent to Charles I,
      King of Great Britain, 1600-1649.
      LJ, XIII, 99.
      f.234-235.
  - DERBY, JAMES STANLEY, 7TH EARL OF, 1607-1651
    - "A copy of the letter from Lord Darby, to commissary general Ireton upon his being commanded to deliver up the Isle of Man" (Box 1)
      [1649 July 12]
      1 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
      MS copy.
      Henry Ireton (1611-1651). Printed in
      Collins, Peerage, V.3.
      f.236.